<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Secure_Ruby_Development_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>

<section id="sect-Secure_Ruby_Development_Guide-Environment-Dependency_management">
	<title>Dependency management</title>
	<para>
		Dependencies in form of gems can be another source of vulnerabilities in Ruby applications.
	</para>

  <section id="sect-Secure_Ruby_Development_Guide-Environment-Outdated_Dependencies">
    <title>Outdated Dependencies</title>
    <para>
      <ulink url="http://bundler.io/">Bundler</ulink> is the de facto standard for managing Ruby application dependencies. Developer can specify required dependencies and their versions in Gemfile and bundler automatically resolves dependencies and prepares environment for application to run in. Bundler freezes exact versions of dependencies in Gemfile.lock and everytime this file is present, depencency resolution step is skipped and exact versions of gems from Gemfile.lock are installed.
    </para>
    <para>
      Freezing versions of dependencies has a security impact. If a dependency is vulnerable and new version contains the fix, Gemfile.lock has to be updated. Detection of outdated versions of dependencies is something that can be automated and several gems help with this using information provided by <ulink url="https://github.com/rubysec/ruby-advisory-db/">rubysec-db</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
      <ulink url="http://www.rubysec.com">Rubysec</ulink> project maintains rubysec-db database of all security advisories related to Ruby libraries. This database covers most of the popular gems and provides data to identify vulnerable and patched versions of dependencies.
    </para>
    <para>
      <ulink url="https://github.com/rubysec/bundler-audit">bundler-audit</ulink> is a gem maintainted by rubysec project that automatically scans Gemfile.lock and reports any unpatched dependencies or insecure sources.
    </para>
    <para>
      <ulink url="https://github.com/appfolio/gemsurance">gemsurance</ulink> also works on top of rubysec-db. Unlike bundler-audit it outputs html report and lists outdated gems as well. Another useful feature is possibility to integrate the check with RSpec and make your tests fail whenever vulnerable dependency is detected.
    </para>
    <para>
      Other gems or services that provide similar functionality include <ulink url="https://github.com/jsuder/holepicker">HolePicker</ulink> and <ulink url="https://gemcanary.com/">gemcanary</ulink>.
    </para>
    <important>
      <para>
        It is highly recommended to set up automated checks for outdated dependencies.
      </para>
    </important>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Vendoring dependencies</title>
    <para>
      Another way of freezing dependencies is checking their source code into vendor folder in application. With bundler this practice becomes obsolete. Another, still valid, usecase is when dependency needs to be slightly modified to suit needs of application.
    </para>
    <para>
      By checking the dependency into the application`s repository, developer takes responsibility of tracking bugs and vulnerabilities and updating vendored gems. However, backporting commits that fix security issues from upstream version will render automatic tools for checking dependencies useless, as they will rely on gem versions, which will not correspond with the vendored code.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Gem signing</title>
    <para>
      Gem signing is already implemented in rubygems and is based on x509 certificates, even though discussion about future implementation is <ulink url="https://github.com/rubygems-trust/rubygems.org/wiki">ongoing</ulink>. There is no PKI, so user who wants to verify gem`s integrity must explicitly download and trust certificate that was used to sign the gem. Establishing trust in certificate of party user has no prior relationship with over internet can be diffucult and unscalable.

      <important>
        <para>
          Assuming user verified the certificate  belongs to the developer it says, signature protects integrity of gem as it is distributed and gives user a mechanism to detect modifications of gem after it was signed.
        </para>
        <para>
          However, signatures do not guarantee trustworthiness of gem author.
        </para>
      </important>
    </para>
    <para>
      Developer can generate his private key and self signed certificate with:
      <programlisting>
$ gem cert --build &lt;email address&gt;
...
$ chmod 600 gem-private_key.pem gem-public_cert.pem
      </programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      This command will generate self-signed 2048 bit RSA with SHA1 certificate (this  configuration is currently hardcoded) stored in PEM format. 
    </para>
    <important>
      <para>
        Generated private key will not be passphrase protected, and it has to be encrypted manually:
<programlisting language="Bash">
$ openssl rsa -des3 -in &lt;private key&gt; -out &lt;encrypted private key&gt;
</programlisting>
      </para>
    </important>
    <para>
      To sign the gem, following needs to be added to gemspec:
      <programlisting language="Ruby">
s.cert_chain = &lt;path to public certificate&gt;
s.signing_key = &lt;path to private key&gt; if $0 =~ /gem\z/
      </programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      After building the gem, one can verify it has been signed with:
      <programlisting>
$ gem spec testgem-1.0.0.gem cert_chain
...
$ tar tf testgem-1.0.0.gem
data.tar.gz
metadata.gz
data.tar.gz.sig
metadata.gz.sig
      </programlisting>
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Installation and policies</title>
      <para>
        To make use of signatures in gems, user has to specify security policy during gem installation (it is turned off by default):

        <programlisting>
$ gem install -P HighSecurity testgem
        </programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>
        There are 4 available security policies:
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>No policy</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Signed packages are treated as unsigned.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>LowSecurity</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Still pretty much no security. Rubygems will make sure signature matches certificate and certificate hasn`t expired.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>MediumSecurity</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>For signed gems, signature is verified against certificate, certificate validity is checked and certificate chain is checked too. Packages from untrusted sources won`t be installed (user has to explicitly trust the cerficate, see below). Unsigned gems are installed normally.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>HighSecurity</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>Same as medium, but unsigned gems are not installed.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <warning>
        <para>Since signatures protect integrity of gem as it`s being distributed from developer to users, the only policy with security impact is <constant>HighSecurity</constant>. With <constant>MediumSecurity</constant>, attacker can always intercept gem, strip signatures, modify it and serve users that accept unsigned gems.</para>
      </warning>
      </para>
      <para>
        To install signed gem under medium or high security policy, user has to download certificate from external source, verify it`s authenticity and explicitly add it to his local database of trusted certificates:
        <programlisting>
$ gem cert --add &lt;certificate&gt;
        </programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>
        This command will store public certificate to <filename>~/.gem/trust</filename> directory. Name of the certificate will contain hexdigest of the subject of certificate, so if users adds another certificate with the same subject as one of the already trusted ones, original one will be overwritten without notice.
      </para>
      <para>
        To avoid overwriting existing certificate, make sure subject of certificate being added is different from certificates that are already trusted:
        <programlisting>
$ openssl x509 -text -in &lt;certificate&gt; | grep Subject:
  Subject: CN=test, DC=example, DC=com
$ gem cert --list
...
        </programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>
        Bundler supports gem signing and trust policies since version 1.3 and user can specify security policy during installation:
        <programlisting>
$ bundle install --trust-policy=HighSecurity
        </programlisting>

        <warning>
          <para>Gems that are installed by bundler from repository like
            <programlisting>
gem 'jquery-datatables-rails', git: 'git://github.com/rweng/jquery-datatables-rails.git'
            </programlisting>
            bypass security policy, as they are not installed using <command>gem</command> command, but cloned into bundler folder.</para>
        </warning>
      </para>
      <para>
        A small gem <command>bundler_signature_check</command> can be used to check <filename>Gemfile</filename> and determine which gems are signed, with suggestion which security policy can be currently safely used (note that <command>bundler_signature_check</command> is signed and it`s dependencies <command>bundler</command> and <command>rake</command> are likely already installed, so <constant>HighSecurity</constant> can be used):
        <programlisting>
$ gem install -P HighSecurity bundler_signature_check
$ bundler_signature_check
...
        </programlisting>
      </para> 
    </section>
      
    <section>
      <title>References:</title>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <ulink url="http://guides.rubygems.org/security/">Rubygems Security page</ulink>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <ulink url="http://rubygems.rubyforge.org/rubygems-update/Gem/Security.html">Documentation of <classname>Gem::Security</classname> module</ulink>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Ben Smith`s Hacking with gems presentation <ulink url="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z-5bO0Q1J9s">on youtube</ulink>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>